A Guide to the Clarence Trent Papers 1958-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Clarence Trent Papers 1958-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms1985-010
1 container; .5 linear feet.
The Trent papers came to Special Collections Department in two groups. Trent himself donated a small group of papers in 1985. His widow, Mrs. Nellie Trent, donated the balance of the collection in February, 1992.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
Clarence E. Trent was born on September 26, 1904. A native of Northfolk, West Virginia, Trent attended Bluefield Junior College in Bluefield, Virginia, where he earned a two-year academic diploma in 1925. In 1930 and 1931 he earned a BS and an MS in Electrical Engineering at Virginia Polytechnic Institute (now Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University). In 1935 and 1936 he earned BS and MME degrees in Mechanical Engineering at VPI. Trent was appointed an assistant professor at VPI in 1931, teaching at first in the Department of Mathematics. In 1932 he was sent to Bluefield, Virginia, to organize the VPI Engineering Branch School in cooperation with Bluefield College. He served as head of the Branch School for eleven years. He returned to VPI campus in 1943, where he remained until his retirement in 1973, teaching both electrical and mechanical engineering. Trent played an active role in the history of the Virginia Section of the Amercian Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME) from 1945 until his death in 1991. In 1981 he was awarded the grade of Life Fellow of the ASME. Serving on the History and Heritage Committee, Trent was a prime force in the selection of two national mechanical engineering landmarks: the Jackson Ferry Shot Tower at Fort Chiswell, Virginia, and Norfolk and Western Railway's 611 steam locomotive. Trent was the co-author (along with Earl B. Norris) of the book Applied Thermodynamics (New York: McGraw Hill, 1955). He died on December 1, 1991, at the age of 87.
Scope and Content Information
The Trent papers contain materials dealing with his activities in the ASME, the Lutheran Campus Ministry at VPI, and engineering education. Further biographical information on Trent may be found in Folder 1 and 27, the latter of which deals with the Distinguished Alumnus Certificate which Bluefield College awarded him in 1986.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged according to subject matter.
Contents List
- Biographical ca. 1982-89
  - Biographical Information ca. 1982-89 (Box-folder 1-1)
- American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME) 1958-91, n.d.
  - Correspondence 1958 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence 1971-72 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence 1973-81 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence 1982-83 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence 1984-91 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Nominations for honors and officers ca. 1965-79 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Locomotive 2300 1979 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - History of Virginia section of the ASME--documents, drafts, etc. 1979-83 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - "Comments on Prof. C.H. Long's Activities with the ASME" 1980 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Fink Truss Bridge relocation 1980 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - ASME Fellow 1980-81 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - National Historic Mechanical Engineering Landmarks--publications 2-13 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Regional Administration Committee 1982 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - History and Heritage Committee 1982-86 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Jackson Ferry Shot Tower (Wythe County) ASME National Historic Landmark dedication--correspondence, notes, etc. 1980-81 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Jackson Ferry Shot Tower (Wythe County)--photographs 1981 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Jackson Ferry Shot Tower (Wythe County) ASME National Historic Landmark dedication--thank you letters 1981 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Jackson Ferry Shot Tower (Wythe County) ASME National Historic Landmark dedication--newspaper articles, press releases 1981-82 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Jackson Ferry Shot Tower (Wythe County) photocopied formula book n.d. (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Norfolk and Western Class J Locomotive No. 611 AMSE National Historic Landmark dedication--correspondence ca. 1982-85 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - Norfolk and Western Class J Locomotive No. 611 ASME National Historic Landmark dedication--photographs 1984 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Norfolk and Western Class J Locomotive No. 611 ASME National Historic Landmark dedcation--ceremony 1984 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Norfolk and Western Class J Locomotive No. 611 ASME National Historic Landmark dedication--publications ca. 1984-89 (Box-folder 1-24)
- General 1968-77, 1982-86, n.d.
  - Engineering education subject files ca. 1968-77 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Lutheran Campus Ministry 1982-86 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Bluefield College Distinguished Alumnus certificate 1984-86 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Unidentified photographs n.d. (Box-folder 1-28)